なんば　むった
こうほ
＜私達 宇宙飛行士候補生の➡
The next astronaut candidate training exercise is the Comeback Competition.
次なる訓練は｢カムバック
コンペティション｣への挑戦＞
＜パラシュートの展開システムや
せいぎょ
自動制御のローバーを作り➡
It's a contest where you compete to reach the goal
by building everything from the parachute deployment system to the rover.
どのぐらい正確に ゴールに
たどり着けるかを競う大会だ＞
＜私たち Ｅ班のサポート役は…＞
This is the advisor assigned to Team E.
(ピコ)お前らか？
俺と組むはめになった➡
So you're the hopeless team that finished last and was stuck with me?
どうしようもねえ 最下位チｰムは｡
(六太)そうです｡
That's right...
うん｡俺はな…｡
You see...
俺は 君らがどうなろうと
知ったこっちゃねえし｡
I really don't give a damn how you do.
＜この 何とも冴えない
おっさん…ピコ･ノートンだ＞
This old fart
is Pico Norton.
＜いったい 何しに来てんだ？
この人＞
Why is he even here?
SPACE BROTHERS
You've always been in my heart
But you don't say a thing or even smile
We've always been together
We're ignorant, but we believe
All the time I spent with you
Felt like a dream
We connected the stars and drew pictures
To our hearts' content
Let our hearts, shivering in excitement,
Use the sky as a canvas
And merge to form an everlasting image
#57 An Engineer's Switch
(通信:飛行士)こちら ルｰニエ２号
ｱｯﾊﾟｰｽﾃｰｼﾞ分離完了｡➡
This is Luniere 2.
Upper stage has been detached.
We're on course to the moon.
きどう
無事 月への軌道に乗っかった｡
(セルゲイ)どうした アズマ
ヒビトが心配か？
What's wrong, Azuma?
Worried about Hibito?
No.
あずま
(吾妻)いや 月で奴に会うのが
楽しみなだけだ｡
I can't wait to meet him on the moon.
Japanese astronaut Azuma Takio is currently on board Russian spacecraft Luniere 2,
[ﾗｼﾞｵ](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)日本人宇宙飛行士
たきお
吾妻滝生さんらを➡
乗せた ロシアの宇宙船･ルーニエ
２号が カザフスタンの➡
which launched successfully from the Baikonur Cosmodrome.
バイコヌール宇宙基地から
打ち上げられ無事成功しました｡➡
現在 月へ向かっている
吾妻さんらは…｡
The crew currently headed for the moon is...
ハァ…こんなもんか｡
Of course...
Okay! Okay, okay, okay. I expected this result.
まあね まあまあ…
そうてい
想定内 想定内｡➡
I didn't warn you guys, but I expected this.
言ってなかったけど 想定内！
Anyway, let's pretend that the capsule landed safely,
とりあえず パラシュートが
ちゃんと開いて➡
今の着地が うまくいったと
仮定しましてぇ｡➡
予定では この筒から こう
ローバーが飛び出してですね｡
and the rover was able to exit on its own.
そして こんな感じで
出動！
And there it goes.
The rover drives itself straight to the goal flag!
走行は すべて自動制御｡
目指すは ゴールフラッグ｡
キャンサット まっしぐら～！
Straight to the CanSat.
あ！あ～…｡
(せりか)はまった｡
It's stuck...
いや こいつは…｡
《想定外》
I wasn't
expecting this.
(ケンジ)もう一回 やってみよう｡
Let's try again.
(新田)とりあえず ロケットを
回収しに行くか｡
We need to go get the rocket.
ふわぁあ～｡
あ～あ｡
コンペまで あと５日しかないのに
課題が山積みだな｡➡
We only have five days until the competition ends,
and we still have a lot to do.
パラシュートは からまって
開かないし ローバーは➡
The parachute got tangled up and won't open.
The rover's slow and won't move far.
遅い上に すぐ止まる｡
１０メートルも進まない｡
Ten meters is the farthest we've gone.
ちょっとしたカベに当たったり
くぼみに落ち込むだけで➡
If it runs into a barrier or uneven ground,
ダメになるみたいだね｡
it stops.
《まるで…俺のようだな》
Just like
me...
ちょっけい
(ピコ)《タイヤの直径が
ちいせえんだよ｡➡
The tires are too small...
しょうがい
そんなんだから 障害を
越えられねえんだ》
That's why it can't overcome any obstacles.
ハァー…君らの議論を
聞いてるより うちのガキの➡
Killing time with my kid's toys has more value than listening to you guys theorize.
おもちゃの方が まだ
ひまつぶしになる｡
あのさ さっき食堂で こっそり
聞いちゃったんだけどね｡➡
Hey, I overheard some news in the cafeteria.
Sounds like Team C will use a fly-back, rather than a run-back CanSat.
Ｃ班は｢ランバック方式｣
じゃなくて➡
｢フライバック方式｣ってのに
したみたい｡
What is that?
ってことは？
そもそも ローバーを
作らないってこと｡➡
It means they won't need to build a rover.
私たちみたいに パラシュートで
ロｰバｰを着地させるんじゃなくて➡
Instead of dropping the rover by parachute like we are,
キャンサットが グライダーで空を
移動して 自動コントロールで➡
the CanSat uses a glider to move through the sky,
automatically navigating to make a pinpoint landing at the goal flag.
ゴｰルフラｯグ付近に ピンポイント
着地させるって作戦よ｡
そんなのアリなの!?
賢いな それなら➡
Is that allowed?
That's clever.
No need to worry about uneven ground.
おうとつ
地面の凹凸も 関係ない｡
I'm starting to think we've been wasting our time.
なんか 急に俺らのやり方が
ムダに思えてきたぞ…｡
ど どうしよう…｡
Wh-What now?
俺らも その方式にするか？
今なら まだ間に合うかもよ｡
Should we also make the switch?
We still have time.
お～い アホかね 君らは｡
Hey...
Are you guys morons?
Have you stopped to consider the cons to that method?
そのやり方に 弱点がないか
ちゃんと頭で考えたか？
君らにも 脳みそはついてんだろ？
そのケツの １メートルほど上に｡
Don't you have any brains?
Located about a meter above your ass?
弱点？
何か弱点あるかな｡
Cons?
Are there any cons?
完ぺきだと思ったけど…｡
It sounded perfect to me.
《空の障害っつったら…鳥か？》
An obstacle in the sky...
Birds?
Is wind an issue?
風…ですか？
その通り！風だ｡
Exactly!
The wind.
《だよね…》
Of course.
大会会場 一帯の上空は この時期
かなり強い風が吹いている｡➡
This time of year, in the area where the
competition's held, winds are pretty strong.
キャンサットの自動制御程度じゃ
十中八九 制御不能で流される｡➡
Any automated glider will be carried away by the wind.
恥をかきたくなけりゃ
この大会で空中戦は選ぶな｡➡
Unless you're looking to embarrass yourselves, you'll want to stay out of the air.
Stick to the ground.
地を這って行くこったな｡
《初めて まともなコメントを…》
That's the first useful thing he's said.
(シェイン)ヒューウ！
イエス！成功だ！
Yes, it's a success!
The other teams are probably ahead of us with their parachutes and rovers.
(ケンジ)パラシｭートもローバーも
多分 他の班の方が➡
一歩先を行っている｡僕らは まず
ﾛｰﾊﾞｰの問題から片付けていこう｡
Let's start by figuring out the rover.
地面の ちょっとした障害に
負けないローバーにするには➡
What do we need to overcome any ground obstacles?
どうすればいいか…｡
障害をジャンプして➡
Do we need a mechanism to let the rover jump obstacles?
飛び越える装置でも
追加するか｡
それじゃあ 重量も重くなるし
今から システムを➡
That adds weight,
and programming a system would be hard in the time we have left.
作るだけでも難しいぞ｡
(ピー ピー…)
もの作りには 失敗することに使う
金と労力が 必要なんだよ｡
When you build something, you must be ready to spend time and money on failure.
おとこ
(ピコ)《あの モジャ男…
思ったより 考え方が➡
That afro has the mind of an engineer.
技術者寄りだな｡元々 同じような
畑に いやがったか？》
Maybe he has a similar background?
プログラムを いじるだけで障害を
かいひ
回避できねえかな アマンティ？
Is it possible to alter the program so the rover avoids obstacles, Amanti?
例えばさ ローバーが
５秒以上 進まなかったら➡
For example...
If five seconds pass with no forward progress,
the rover receives a command to reverse.
少しバックするっていう
命令を加える｡
で 角度を軽くずらして
また走り出す｡
Then the rover turns at a slight angle before proceeding.
《ほぉ…》
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)できると思う｡
(ｹﾝｼﾞ)いいね それ！
やってみよう｡
That should be doable.
Sounds good... Let's try that.
And if possible, I'd like another five or six centimeters on the tire diameter.
あと できれば タイヤの直径を
５～６センチ➡
大きくしたいんだよな～｡
そうすりゃ スピードも増すし➡
That'll help speed up the rover and help it overcome obstacles.
障害も越えやすくなるよ｡
確かに それができると
いいんだけど➡
True...
But the rocket tube is only fifteen centimeters in diameter,
ロケットに入れる 筒の内側が
１５センチだから➡
それ以上のタイヤは 厳しいね｡
so it'd be hard to make the tires bigger.
I would use expandable tires.
かくちょうしき
《俺なら 拡張式のタイヤにする｡
それなら➡
That would give you tires 1.5 times the diameter of the rocket.
筒に入る 元の直径から
１.５倍にはできる｡➡
ただ 奴らにそれを作る
技術は ないか…》
But they probably don't have the ability to make that work.
(ｹﾝｼﾞ)ムッ君 傘みたいに
広がるタイヤは どう？
Mu, is it possible to make tires that expand like umbrellas?
《そうだ｡ほかには ない》
Right, that's the only option.
いいアイデアだと思う｡
けど…｡
It's a good idea, but...
上手く作れれば いいんだけど
パーツが増える分➡
They'll work if built correctly,
but the additional parts might put us over the weight limit.
重量も気になるなぁ｡
No, you can do it and stay under the limit.
きょようはんい
《いや 許容範囲内で できる》
あっ そうだ！
Ah! I know!
タイヤを スポンジで作ろう｡
《何!?》
We can make the tires out of sponge!
What?
スポンジ…ですか？
Out of sponge?
Yep.
スポンジなら ぎゅっと縮めて
筒に入れられるし➡
If we use sponge, we can squeeze it into a tube.
When the time comes, the wheels will expand to the proper size.
走る時には 充分な大きさに
ふくらむ｡それに軽いし➡
And it's a light, cheap material that's easy to shape.
安いし 加工もしやすい｡
着地の時のショックも
やわらげるよ｡
And it'll also help to absorb some shock from landing.
(ｹﾝｼﾞ)そうだね！
いいことだらけ！
最高じゃん それ！
You're right!
That all sounds great!
It's perfect!
《スポンジ…
考えたこともなかった》
Sponge...
I never considered that!
Next comes the parachute.
で 次は
パラシュートだけど…｡
フーン…パラシュートの
｢パ｣ぐらいは➡
I'm willing to give you one piece of advice about the parachute.
教えてやっても いいかな｡
Wow...
《スゲー｡早いのに丁寧》
He's quick and precise...
ふわ～｡
What's with those moves?
《なんなんだよ｡
そのなめらかな手の動きは》
Those hairy old man hands move as gracefully as the hands of a lady wrapping clothing at the store.
《毛深くワイルドな
おっさんの手が➡
まるでラッピングをする女性店員
の手のようにしなやかに動く》
はら～｡
宇宙飛行士が６人もいて
１人も考えなかったのか？
Six astronauts in this room, and none of you looked at this in a different way?
｢キャンサットが本物の
宇宙船だとしたら｣って｡
What if this CanSat were an actual spaceship?
となり
自分の隣にいる宇宙飛行士を
こいつに乗せて➡
While you built this, were you acting as though your fellow astronauts would be riding inside?
打ち上げるつもりで
全部の作業をやってたか？
Also, ladies should fold up the parachute.
ああ それから
パラシュートは女子が たため｡
この班には運よく３人もいる｡
なぜです？
Fortunately, your team has three.
Why is that?
パラシュートの収納作業ってのは
昔から女の仕事だ｡
Traditionally, women have always folded the parachutes.
他の国は どうかしらね～けどな｡
No idea what the practice is elsewhere.
ほら やってみろ｡隣の男の命を
預かったつもりでな｡
Give it a try.
Pretend the life of the man next to you is in your hands.
R-Right.
あっはい｡
《命を…》
あっお願いします｡
His life is in my hands...
I-I'm all yours...
落ちたら…ごめんなさい｡
If you crash, I'm sorry.
せん
だきょう
ハー 繊細で妥協が許されない
作業が➡
One theory holds that women are more suited to delicate, precise work.
女向きだからという説もあるがな｡
It started during World War II.
起源を言えば第二次世界大戦だ｡
戦場へ行った夫や
ボーイフレンドに無事に➡
Women, wanting their husbands and boyfriends to come home alive,
帰ってきてほしいっていう
願掛けの意味で➡
folded the parachutes,
パラシュートが開く生命線になる
収納作業は女がやるようになった｡
ensuring they would open properly.
要するにパラシュートってのは…｡
It was the power of love.
愛で開く｡
I see...
《なるほど…》
Oops, I screwed up...
おっと うっかりだぜ｡➡
That was more than one piece of advice.
パラシュートの｢ト｣まで
教えちまった｡
Hey, you're good, Mu.
(ケンジ)おっ うまいね ムッ君｡
手つきが職人みたい｡
You have the hands of a pro.
フフフ…まあね 前の会社で
さんざん模型とか作ってたからな｡
Of course.
At my old job, I spent a lot of time building models.
うおっほ！
これだよ これ！
There it is.
(北村)障害物に当たったら
ルートを変えるのがここ｡
Here's the command to change course after an obstacle is encountered.
ジーピーエス
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)そのあとＧＰＳから
座標を拾って➡
The rover will then use GPS to map a new route.
新しい最適ルートを
探すようにしたんです｡
Oh, that's perfect!
おお！完ぺきじゃん！
動作確認モードで試運転します｡
Let's do a test run to see if it works.
(ピピッ ピピッ)
こいつ こんなに
ピコピコ鳴ってたっけ？
Did it beep this much before?
Huh? Is there an error somewhere?
あれ？なんかミスっちゃったかな｡
It won't stop beeping.
ピコピコうるせ～な｡
I don't think we need all this beeping.
このピコピコという音は
いらね～んじゃねぇか？
Yeah, we don't need the beeping.
そうだな いらね～な ピコピコは｡
(北村)いらないね ピコピコ
ごめん なんとかするね｡
We don't need any beeping.
Sorry, I'll figure something out.
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)日本人宇宙飛行士
吾妻滝生さんらの乗る➡
The spacecraft Luniere 2, with Japanese astronaut Azuma Takio, has reached lunar orbit.
宇宙船･ルーニエ２号が
月周回軌道に到着！➡
着陸船ナウカは無事
月面に降り立ちました｡
The lunar module Nauka has landed safely on the moon.
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)
ロシア人と日本人のトリオが
月面に到着｡➡
The three Russian and Japanese astronauts
ＣＥＳ－５１のクルーとの
ご対面を数時間後にひかえます｡➡
will meet the CES-51 crew in a few hours.
ＣＥＳ－５１のクルーは現在➡
Currently, the CES-51 crew is in transit to Nauka's landing site.
ナウカの着陸ポイントに
向かって移動中です｡
何してるんです？今日の訓練は
もう終わっているはずですよ｡
What are you doing?
Training is over for the day, Mr. Nanba Mutta.
ミスター･ナンバ･ムッタ｡
ビンスさん…｡
質問の答えを｡
Vince...
Answer the question.
Well...
ああ…いや…｡
Pico invited me to have a drink with him.
さそ
ピコに誘われまして…
酒に付き合えって｡
ピコが…君をですか？
Pico invited you?
ええ なぜだか僕だけ｡
For some reason, I was the only one.
《うっ…な 何だろう｡
この冷たい視線は…》
H-His eyes are so cold...
《まるで俺をパセリでも
見るような目で…》
He's looking at me like I'm parsley.
元自動車開発会社勤務…でしたね
ミスター･ナンバ｡
I believe you once worked at an automobile manufacturer, Mr. Nanba.
Huh?
えっ まあ そうですけど｡
Yes, that's right.
じゃあ 車は好きでしょう｡
一緒にドライブを｡
Then you must like cars.
Care to join me for a drive?
えっ!?ああ いや でも
これからピコと｡
(ビンス)私も これから➡
Huh?
B-But I need to go...
I also made a promise to drink with Pico tonight.
ピコと飲む約束をしています｡
Well? Are you getting in? Decide quickly.
どうします？乗るのか
乗らないのか早く決めて下さい｡➡
Life is short.
人生は短いんです｡
I didn't know that afro was Hibito's big brother...
《あのモジャ男が
ヒビトの兄貴だったとはな…》
しんぼう
《あと５日…あと５日の辛抱だ》
Five more days.
I just have to deal with this for five more days...
In five days, Hibito and the other astronauts will return in Orion.
《ヒビトたちを乗せたオリオンが
５日後に帰ってきて➡
The moment the parachutes deploy...
パラシュートがバッと
開いた瞬間➡
I'll finally be free.
ようやく俺は解放される》
スピードを少し上げますよ｡
I'm going to speed up.
As you place your hopes on the distant moon
And leave on your journey
You smile in spite of your loneliness
Because you believe in yourself
It doesn't matter if your wings don't match
Spread them out
As you
begin your long journey (try now) (try now)
I'm sure you can make it
Please don't hesitate
to move straight forward
You took
all your pain and sorrow (no more) (no more)
And turned it into your strength
So I'm sure even your destiny to fight many a battle
Is on your side
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#58 Earnest Failure
I end up drinking with Pico and Vince.
＜ピコとビンスさんと
酒を飲むことになった俺＞
Why was I invited?
＜何で呼ばれたんだ？
２人が胸に秘めた➡
They tell me a story from their childhood.
少年時代の出来事が
明らかになる＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Earnest Failure"
＜本気の失敗には 価値がある＞
An earnest failure still has meaning.